Martha Foote Crow Papers
Martha Foote Crow Papers
1885-1921.
Crow, Martha Foote, 1854-1924.
3.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, educator, lecturer. Includes correspondence, 1885-1921; writings; and memorabilia.
144578
Biographical History
Martha Foote Crow, educator and writer, was born in 1854 in Sackets Harbor, New York, the daughter of the Reverend John B. and Mary Pendexter (Stilphen) Foote. She received a Ph.D. in 1885 from Syracuse University. In 1884 she married archaeologist John M. Crow, who died in 1891.
Mrs. Crow served on the faculty of Ives Seminary, Waynesburg College, and Wellesley College, becoming principal of Grinnell College in 1884. In 1891 she became assistant professor of English literature at the University of Chicago, and in 1900 was appointed dean of women at Northwestern University.
In addition to lecturing before many scholarly societies, Crow was an active member of the Browning Society, the League of American Pen Women, the Poetry Society of America, and the General Foundation of Women's Clubs. Among her published works are Elizabethan Sonnet Cycles (1896), The World Above (1905), Elizabeth Barrett Browning (1907), Harriet Beecher Stowe, a Biography (1913), The American Country Girl (1915), Lafayette (1916), and Christ in the Poetry of Today (1917).
Mrs. Crow's home was in Chicago, Illinois, where she died on January 1, 1924.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Martha Foote Crow Papers comprise Biographical material, Correspondence, Writings, and Memorabilia of the American educator, lecturer, and author. Spanning the years 1885 to 1921, the Correspondence-Subject file (Boxes 1-2) is arranged alphabetically and includes family letters as well as literary correspondence (Katharine Bates, Anna Hempstead Branch, Amelia Josephine Burr, Grace Hazard Conkling, Edwin Markham, Harriet Monroe, Edwin Arlington Robinson, Sara Teasdale, Elinor Wylie). In addition, there is a sizable collection of organizational correspondence including that of Alpha Phi, the Colorado Federation of Women's Clubs, the General Federation of Women's Clubs, the League of American Pen Women, the National Women's Christian Temperance Union, and the Poetry Society of America. Perhaps the most interesting of the organizational correspondence refers to the expulsion of George Sylvester Viereck from the Poetry Society of America.
Writings (Boxes 3-7) include (for a given title) any combination of background information, typescript manuscripts, production material, publicity, and reviews of various of Martha Foote Crow's books including Christ in the Poetry of Today, Elizabethan Sonnet Cycles, "Enigma" (unpublished), and Lafayette. Also included are the typescript manuscripts for a number of Crow's essays, which range in subject from poetry to education and women's issues. The bulk of the Writings are Crow's lecture notes, which have been arranged by topic and include Bible history, Robert Browning, chirography, drama, George Meredith, and the character of the 19th century.
Memorabilia (Box 8) includes miscellaneous clippings (newspaper clippings which refer to Crow have been placed with biographical material in Box 1), photographs, and the writings of others, some of which are poetic tributes to Crow.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Literature -- American Poetry; Women Authors; Bates, Katharine Lee, 1859-1929.; Branch, Anna Hempstead, 1875-1937.; Conkling, Grace Hazard, 1878-1958.; Crow, Martha Foote, 1854-1924.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.; Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936.; Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933.; Wylie, Elinor, 1885-1928.; Alpha Phi.; General Federation of Women's Clubs.; League of American Pen Women.; National Women's Christian Temperance Union.; Poetry Society of America.; American poetry -- 20th century.; American poetry -- Women authors.; Educators -- United States.; Lecturers -- United States.; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century.; Poets, American -- Correspondence.; Women authors, American.; Women educators -- United States.; Women poets, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Authors.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Foote, 1932.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject file
  - Biographical material, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - A, one folder (Box 1)
  - Allen, Lyman Whitney, 1919-1921 (Box 1)
  - Alpha Phi, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Armstrong, A. Joseph, 1920 (Box 1)
  - B, one folder (Box 1)
  - Babbitt, Shirley D., 1920 (Box 1)
  - Babcock, Edwina Stanton, 1917; 1920 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Karle Wilson, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Barker, Elsa, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Barr, Frances Greeno, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Barrows, Mary Minerva, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Bates, Katharine Lee, 1917; 1920 (Box 1)
  - Best, Nolan Rice, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Blanchard, Phyllis Mary, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Boole, Ella Alexander, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Boston Browning Society, 1920-1921; 1898; printed material (Box 1)
  - Botsford, Florence Hudson, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Branch, Anna Hempstead, 1917-1920 (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, June, ca. 1919 (Box 1)
  - Burr, Amelia Josephine, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Burt, Maxwell Struthers, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Burton, Guthrie, undated (Box 1)
  - Burton, Ruth Guthrie Thomson Harding, See Burton, Guthrie
  - C, one folder (Box 1)
  - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Cassidy, Ina Sizer, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Cogswell, Dorothy, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Colorado Federation of Women's Clubs, 1919; undated; printed material (Box 1)
  - Conant, Isabel Fiske, 1921; undated (Box 1)
  - Conkling, Grace Hazard, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Coolbrith, Ina D., 1920 (Box 1)
  - Crew, Helen Coale, undated (Box 1)
  - D, one folder (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Gustav, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Dawson, Miles M., 1917; 1920 (Box 1)
  - Day, James R., 1920 (Box 1)
  - Deutsch, Babette, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Dransfield, Jane, See Poetry Society of America
  - Driscoll, Louise, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - E, one folder (Box 1)
  - F, one folder (Box 1)
  - Faulks, Theodosia, See Garrison, Theodosia
  - Fiske, Horace Spencer, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Flanner, Hildegarde, holograph poems (Box 1)
  - Flugel, Ewald, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Foote (parents), 1901; undated (Box 1)
  - Foote, Elizabeth L., 1920-1921; undated (Box 1)
  - Foote, William Y., 1900-1902; undated (Box 1)
  - Foster, Jeanne Robert, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Frank, Florence Kiper, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Frasier, Scottie McKenzie, 1920 (Box 1)
  - G, one folder (Box 1)
  - Garrison, Theodosia, undated (Box 1)
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs, 1920; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Gordon, Anna Adams, 1919; 1921 (Box 1)
  - Gorman, Herbert Sherman, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Gray, Agnes Kendrick, undated (Box 1)
  - Guiney, Louise Imogen, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Guiterman, Arthur, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Gunsaulus, Frank W., 1920 (Box 1)
  - H, one folder (Box 1)
  - Hagedorn, Hermann, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Harding, Ruth Guthrie, See Burton, Guthrie
  - Hayes, L. Newton, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Hazard, Caroline, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Henderson, Alice Corbin, undated (Box 1)
  - Horder, W. Garrett, 1919 (Box 1)
  - I, one folder (Box 1)
  - J, one folder (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Helen Louise, 1919 (Box 1)
  - K, one folder (Box 1)
  - Kelley, William Valentine, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Kemp, Harold, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - King, Horatio Collins, 1915 (Box 1)
  - L (Box 1)
  - League of American Pen Women, Inc., 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Lee, Muna, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Lieberman, Elias, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Lindsey, Frederick Brooks, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Lindsey, William, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Lomax, John Avery, 1920 (Box 1)
  - M, one folder (Box 2)
  - MacClintock, Porter Lander, undated (Box 2)
  - McClurg, Alexander Caldwell, undated (Box 2)
  - McElroy, Cora Cleona Clark, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Markham, Anna Catherine, undated (Box 2)
  - Markham, Edwin, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Melcher, Frederic Gershom, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Millen, Mabel, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Molineux, Marie Ada, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Moody, Harriet, 1919-1921 (Box 2)
  - Morrison, Charles Clayton, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Morton, David, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Mosher, Thomas Bird, 1896 (Box 2)
  - N, one folder (Box 2)
  - National Woman's Christian Temperance Union, See Gordon, Anna A.
  - Naylor, Emmett Hay, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Naylor, Ruth C., undated (Box 2)
  - Nelson, Lawrence Emerson, 1918 (Box 2)
  - New York Browning Society, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Nicholson, Meredith, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Noguchi, Yone, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Norton, Clara Mamre, 1917; printed material (Box 2)
  - O (Box 2)
  - Oliver, Wade Wright, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
  - O'Sheel, Shaemas, See Poetry Society of America
  - P, one folder (Box 2)
  - Paine, Paul M., 1919-1920 (Box 2)
  - Parker, Cornelia Stanton, undated (Box 2)
  - Payne, William Morton, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Peattie, Elia (and Robert), 1920 (Box 2)
  - Peters, Iva Lowther, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Pettus, Martha Elvira, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Piper, Edwin Ford, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Poetry Society of America, 1917-1920; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Pollard, Alfred W., 1894-1897; undated (Box 2)
  - G. P. Putnam's, 1920 (Box 2)
  - R, one folder (Box 2)
  - Reese, Lizette Woodworth, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Revell, Fleming H., 1917 (Box 2)
  - Rice, Cale Young, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Rice, Paul North, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Rice, Ruth Mason, See League of American Pen Women, Inc.
  - Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, undated (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Roth, Samuel, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Rugg, Winnifred King, 1920 (Box 2)
  - S, one folder (Box 2)
  - Schauffler, Robert Haven, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Schola Poetarum Americana - manuscript poems (Box 2)
  - Scollard, Clinton, undated (Box 2)
  - Siegrist, Mary, undated (Box 2)
  - Slack, Elvira J., undated (Box 2)
  - Smalley, Frank, 1896; 1920 (Box 2)
  - Smith, May Riley, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Squires, Vernon Purinton, 1917; 1920 (Box 2)
  - Stott, Roscoe Gilmore, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Sturgis, Lyman B., 1920 (Box 2)
  - T, one folder (Box 2)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1917; 1920 (Box 2)
  - Thomas, Edith Matilda, 1917; 1920 (Box 2)
  - Thomson, Ruth Sanders, See Alpha Phi
  - Tolman, Albert Harris, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Triggs, Oscar Lovell, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Trine, Grace Steele Hyde, 1920 (Box 2)
  - U, one folder (Box 2)
  - V, one folder (Box 2)
  - Viereck, George Sylvester, See also Poetry Society of America (Box 2)
  - Vilas, Faith, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
  - W, one folder (Box 2)
  - Welles, Winifred, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Widdemer, Margaret, undated (Box 2)
  - Wilkinson, Marguerite Ogden Bigelow, 1917; 1921 (Box 2)
  - Winke, Charles, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Winter, Alice Ames, See General Federation of Women's Clubs
  - Wylie, Elinor, 1920-1921 (Box 2)
  - Y, one folder (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Books:
    - Christ in the Poetry of Today, background material (Box 3)
    - Christ in the Poetry of Today, page proofs (Box 3)
    - Christ in the Poetry of Today, publicity material (Box 3)
    - Christ in the Poetry of Today, reviews (Box 3)
    - Elizabethan Sonnet Cycles, correspondence, notes (Box 3)
    - Elizabethan Sonnet Cycles, reviews (Box 3)
    - "Enigma" (unpublished), background material (Box 3)
    - "Enigma" (unpublished), typescript ms.; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - "Enigma" (unpublished), ms. fragments (Box 3)
    - "Enigma" (unpublished), typescript ms. Chapter I-VI (Box 3)
    - "Enigma" (unpublished), typescript ms. Chapter VII-XXXVI; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Lafayette, background material (Box 4)
    - Lafayette, correspondence, notes (Box 4)
  - Essays:
    - "A Book of the Skokie", typescript ms. with holograph corrections (Box 4)
    - "The Immigrant", typescript ms. (Box 4)
    - "The Immigrant in American Poetry", typescript ms. (Box 4)
    - "Parentage", typescript ms. (Box 4)
    - "The Social Burden", typescript ms. (Box 4)
    - "Woman", typescript ms. (Box 4)
    - Untitled, re: Montessori Schools (Box 4)
  - Lecture notes:
    - Bible history, 21 folders (Box 5)
    - Robert Browning, 10 folders (Box 6)
    - Chirography, 1 folder (Box 6)
    - Drama, 14 folders (Box 6, 7)
    - George Meredith, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - The Nineteenth century, 10 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Miscellany:
    - Unidentified, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Financial material (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Writings of others, 3 folders (Box 8)